Guide to The Billie Jean King Collection 1901-2019 (bulk, 1940-2019) MS 3147
New-York Historical Society
Billie Jean King collection
1901-2021 (bulk, 1940-2021)
New-York Historical Society
King, Billie Jean
MS 3147
80 Linear feet in 42 record cartons, 2 document boxes, 21 flat boxes, 1 oversize long box, and one oversize folder
Billie Jean Moffitt King is a tennis legend, holding 39 Grand Slam titles, and a champion for equality. King made advances for women's rights to equitable pay and recognition through her advocacy and participation as one of the Original 9, on the Virginia Slims Tour, with the founding of the Women's Tennis Association, the founding of the Women's Sports Foundation, co-creating womenSports magazine, and co-founding of World TeamTennis, a mixed-gender professional tennis league. King is also widely known for her 1973 victory over Bobby Riggs in the "Battle of the Sexes" tennis match. The Billie Jean King collection includes documents, scrapbooks, publications, photographs, tennis results from Grand Slam tournaments, memorabilia, and artifacts generated and collected by Billie Jean King throughout her life and career as an athlete, an advocate for equality, and as a public figure.
Arrangement
During processing the archivist devised an arrangement of ten series. In the rare instances of existing folders, original folder titles were maintained. The final order of the collection and series division is based primarily on material format.
The collection is arranged in ten series:
Series I. Early life and Moffitt family
Series II. Scrapbooks
Series III. Subject files
Series IV. Speeches
Series V. Awards and recognition
Series VI. Correspondence
Series VII. Print matter
Series VIII. Photographs
Series IX. Audiovisual and digital formats
Series X. Artifacts and memorabilia
Biographical / Historical
Billie Jean King is a tennis legend and champion for equality. Widely known for her victory over Bobby Riggs in the "Battle of the Sexes" tennis match, King made advances for women's rights to equitable pay and recognition through her participation as one of the Original 9, playing on the Virginia Slims Tour, as founder of the Women's Tennis Association, as founder of the Women's Sports Foundation, and as co-founder of World TeamTennis, a mixed-gender league. BJK also founded Billie Jean King Enterprises and Billie Jean King Leadership Initiative to address equality and inclusion issues in the workplace. King, a lesbian, has also advocated for LGBTQ rights and served on the Board of Directors of the Elton John AIDS Foundation as a founding board member and Honorary Lifetime President.
In 2009, King was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom, becoming the first female athlete to be honored with the nation's highest civilian honor. President Barack Obama honored King, saying "...we honor what she calls all of the off the court stuff. What she did to broaden the reach of the game, to change how women athletes and women everywhere view themselves and to give everyone, regardless of gender or sexual orientation, including my two daughters, a chance to compete both on the court and in life."
Billie Jean Moffitt was born November 22, 1943, in Long Beach, California to Mildred Rose "Betty" Jerman Moffitt and Willis "Bill" Jefferson Moffitt. BJK began playing tennis in her youth with free tennis instruction on public courts and began playing in sectional and national USLTA tournaments. From 1961-1964 BJK attended California State University, Los Angeles while competing in tennis tournaments, including Wightman Cup and Fed Cup, the annual international team competition and world cup of women's professional tennis. In the fall of 1964 BJK traveled to Australia to perfect her game working with the Australian players. In 1968 she became a contract pro.
In 1965 Billie Jean Moffitt married Cal State classmate Larry King. Throughout their marriage, BJK and Larry King collaborated on the promotion of tennis through the ownership of tournaments on the Virginia Slims pro circuit and the leadership of World TeamTennis. In 1974 BJK and Larry King co-founded and published womenSports magazine. BJK and Larry King divorced in 1987. BJK and life partner Ilana Kloss, a former World No.1 doubles player and former CEO of World TeamTennis, have been together since 1979. BJK and Kloss joined the ownership group of the Los Angeles Dodgers in 2018, the Los Angeles Sparks in 2019, and Angel City FC in 2020.
BJK holds 39 Grand Slam titles: 12 singles titles, 16 women's doubles titles, and 11 mixed doubles titles. In 1961, Billie Jean Moffitt and Karen Hantze Susman became the youngest team to win the Ladies Doubles Championships at Wimbledon. In 1966, BJK won her first major singles championship at Wimbledon and was ranked as the number one player in the world in women's tennis. She held the world number 1 ranking from 1966-1968, 1971-1972, and in 1974. Between 1961 and 1979, BJK won 20 Wimbledon titles, 13 United States titles (four singles), four French titles (one singles), and two Australian titles (one singles). In 1972, she won the U.S. Open, French Open, and Wimbledon, earning three Grand Slam titles in one year. BJK's overall Open Era titles is 168 with an overall record of Singles, Doubles, and Mixed of 782-192.
Throughout the 1970s, BJK campaigned for equal prize money to bridge the pay gap between men and women in professional tennis. In September 1970, defying the United States Lawn Tennis Association and in response to its lack of action regarding the pay disparity, BJK and eight other players accepted a $1 contract from tennis promoter Gladys Heldman in Houston as part of the "Original 9." Their vision had three goals: 1. To make sure any girl in the world if she was good enough would have a place to compete; 2. That girl and women athletes would be appreciated for their accomplishments, not just their looks; and 3. That women would be able to make a living. Their courage led to the formation of the Virginia Slims Tour. A culmination of BJK's efforts were realized in 1973 when the US Open became the first Grand Slam to offer equal prize money. The Australian Open joined in 2001, and it wouldn't be until 2007 that Wimbledon and The French Open had equal pay.
In 1973, BJK founded the Women's Tennis Association and became its first president. On September 20, 1973, BJK faced and defeated Bobby Riggs in the famed "Battle of the Sexes" match at the Houston Astrodome in front of 30,472 fans and an estimated worldwide television audience of nearly 90 million people.
In 1974, BJK founded the Women's Sports Foundation, dedicated to protecting the sports provisions of Title IX, and approached Charles Schulz, creator of the Peanuts comic strip, to join the Board of Trustees, and he became an advocate for women's sports. The WSF continues to build a future where every girl and woman has the opportunity to participate in sport and realize her power, potential, and leadership skills. King co-founded World TeamTennis and became the commissioner of WTT in 1981, making her the first woman commissioner in pro sports. In addition to the professional league, a recreational league was played throughout the country. In 2017, after forty-two years, BJK sold her majority ownership of WTT. Along with her partner Ilana Kloss, and their friend Elton John, BJK established World TeamTennis Smash Hits in 1992 as an annual all-star charity tennis match for the Elton John AIDS Foundation. BJK captained the U.S. Olympic women's tennis teams in 1996 and 2000.
Amongst many career distinctions and awards, on August 28, 2006, BJK was honored with the renaming of the National Tennis Center, home of the U.S. Open as the "USTA Billie Jean King National Tennis Center" for her contributions to tennis, sports, and society both on and off the court. In 1990 BJK was named one of "100 Most Important Americans of the 20th Century" by LIFE Magazine. In 2020 Federation Cup was renamed the Billie Jean King Cup in her honor. BJK was captain of nine Fed Cup teams for the United States. BJK was inducted into the International Tennis Hall of Fame as a player in 1987 and again, in 2021, as a part of the Original 9.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from Billie Jean King, 2019.
Scope and Contents
The Billie Jean King collection includes documents, scrapbooks, publications, photographs, memorabilia, and artifacts generated and collected by BJK throughout her life and career as an athlete, founder of Women's Tennis Association and Women's Sports Foundation, advocate for equality, and public figure.
Personal documents include early school records, family ephemera, and family photographs, as well as correspondence. Documentation of BJK's tennis career includes photographs of matches, albums of clippings assembled by BJK's family, newspaper clippings files, and publications including articles written on BJK. Publications and photographs in the collection also capture the landscape of women's tennis over time, the activities of the World TeamTennis professional and recreational league, and additional prominent athletes in the sport from the 1960s to 2000s.
The speech files provide insight into BJK's personal history, values, and mission as expressed in her own words while addressing various audiences. Honors and certificates awarded to BJK reflect her wide-ranging influence as a tennis champion, voice for women's sport, and advocate for pay equity, gender equality, and human rights.
There are a number of items throughout the collection documenting the career and recognition of BJK's life partner Ilana Kloss.
Throughout the finding aid several abbreviations are used, notably BJK for Billie Jean King, WSF for Women's Sports Foundation, WTA for the Women's Tennis Association, and WTT for the league World TeamTennis.
Accruals
The collection is open for additional material that may be donated over time by Billie Jean King.
Related Materials
Related artifacts and objects, including awards and trophies; athletic wear, including Ted Tinling designs; and sporting equipment, are held by the New-York Historical Society Museum. Inquiries about these objects can be directed to the Museum at: nyhscollections@nyhistory.org.
Lesbians; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Tennis -- Tournaments; Tennis players -- United States -- Photographs; Women athletes.; Women -- Employment.; Women tennis players -- United States; John, Elton; Riggs, Bobby, 1918-1995; Women's Sports Foundation; World TeamTennis Franchise, Inc.
- Series I. Early life and Moffitt family, 1933-2014; 1 Linear feet in 1 record carton and 1 flat file
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains material documenting the early life of BJK and the Moffitt family. Documents from early life include school progress reports, school assignments and notebooks, and high school yearbooks. Family documents include academic and career records for members of the Moffitt family, particularly BJK's parents and brother Randy Moffitt, a Major League Baseball pitcher. Also included is a file of postcards and correspondence sent by BJK to her family and correspondence shared amongst the family. Material in this series dates from 1933-2014.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in two subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Early life
  Subseries I.B. Moffitt family
  - Subseries I.A. Early life, 1943-2006 (bulk, 1949-1961); 0.5 Linear feet in 1 record carton
    Subseries I.A. includes records documenting BJK's childhood and early education. Materials include documents from Sunday School at First Church of the Brethren Church, school progress reports and report cards from Long Beach Public Schools, academic assignments and notebooks, high school yearbooks, a sorority fabric swatch, programs for BJK's high school commencement ceremony, and a copy of BJK's birth certificate. The bulk date of material is 1949-1961, with the birth certificate dated 2006 to reflect the year requested and delivered.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Baby book (2 folders), 1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-2)
      BJK's Baby Book, including pasted baby cards sent from family members and additional inserted greeting cards for other family occasions.
    - Los Cerritos School progress reports, 1949-1953 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
      Contains progress reports from BJK's time in primary and elementary school at Los Cerritos School, Long Beach, California.
    - Sunday school, 1952-1955 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
      Contains certificates for completing courses in Sunday school and Christian Education from the First Church of the Brethren, Long Beach, California and the Long Beach Council of Churches, and bulletin from First Church of the Brethren that includes photograph of Mildred and Bill Moffitt.
    - Los Cerritos School Class of 1955 booklet (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
      Contains booklet of signatures of BJK's 6th grade classmates and teacher from Los Cerritos Elementary School.
    - Hughes Junior High School, 1955-1958 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
      Contains progress reports and certificates for BJK from Hughes Junior High School, Long Beach Public Schools, Long Beach, California.
    - Tenth grade story "Thump, thump, thump, beat my heart", circa 1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
      Contains handwritten story by BJK about her future and first trip to Wimbledon.
    - Long Beach Polytechnic High School progress reports, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
      Contains progress reports for BJK in courses at Polytechnic High School, Long Beach, California.
    - High school course notebooks and writings (2 folders), 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-11)
      Contains several notebooks with course notes and writing assignments from BJK's high school classes.
    - Caerulea yearbook, 1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
      Long Beach Polytechnic High School yearbook from BJK's sophomore year. BJK is pictured on page 133.
    - Caerulea yearbook, 1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
      Long Beach Polytechnic High School yearbook from BJK's junior year. BJK is pictured on page 127.
    - Caerulea yearbook, 1961 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
      Long Beach Polytechnic High School yearbook from BJK's senior year. BJK is pictured on pages 32, 58-59, 147, 174.
    - Zayn sorority swatch, circa 1961 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
      Contains blue felt sorority swatch with "Z" insignia of the Zayn service sorority BJK belonged to while attending Long Beach Polytechnic High School.
    - High school commencement, 1961 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
      Contains documents from BJK's graduation from Polytechnic High School, Long Beach, California in June 1961.
    - Pitchfork Los Angeles State College yearbook (4 folders), 1961-1964 (Offsite-box 67, Folder 1-4)
    - Copy of birth certificate issued by County of Los Angeles Registrar-Recorder/County Clerk, 2006 January 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
      Contains a copy requested in 2006 of BJK's birth certificate and affidavit to correct original birth certificate's error in spelling Billie Jean King's middle name as "Jaan" on original certificate. The date of original birth certificate document (not included in folder) is November 22, 1943, and the date of original affidavit for correction document (not included in folder) is May 11, 1955.
  - Subseries I.B. Moffitt family, 1933-2014; 0.5 Linear feet in 1 record carton and 1 flat file
    Subseries I.B. includes material documenting the lives and careers of the Moffitt family. Material includes academic records, certificates, event programs, postcards, and letters. Family members represented include BJK's mother and father, Mildred Rose "Betty" Jerman Moffitt and Willis "Bill" Jefferson Moffitt, a police officer and firefighter, and brother Randall "Randy" James Moffitt, a Major League Baseball pitcher. Additional family members documented include paternal grandmother Blanche G. Moffitt and niece Alysha Marie Moffitt. Material dates from 1933-2014.
    Arranged by Moffitt family member, followed by material generated and shared amongst multiple family members.
    - Mildred "Betty" Jerman Moffitt, 1940-2014 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
      Contains documents pertaining to Mildred Rose "Betty" Jerman Moffitt, BJK's mother.
    - Mildred "Betty" Jerman Moffitt certificates, 1926-1941 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 1)
      Contains "Cradle Role Certificate" from the First Brethren Sunday School of Long Beach, California, 1926 and diploma from The Harbell College of Cosmetology, 1941.
    - Bill Moffitt, 1933-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
      Contains documents pertaining to Willis "Bill" Jefferson Moffitt, BJK's father.
    - Randy Moffitt early life, 1954-1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
      Contains documents pertaining to BJK's brother Randall "Randy" James Moffitt's childhood and youth.
    - Randy Moffitt baseball career, 1965-1983 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
      Contains a signed photograph, correspondence, baseball game programs, and an issue of Sports Illustrated with article on Randy Moffitt's professional baseball career.
    - Randy Moffitt baseball cards, 1973-1983 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
      Contains Randy Moffitt baseball cards from his time with the San Francisco Giants, Houston Astros, and Toronto Blue Jays.
    - Randy Moffitt baseball career clippings, 1965-1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
      Contains newspaper clippings pertaining to Randy Moffitt's career as a Major League Baseball pitcher.
    - Blanche G. Moffitt, 1970-1981 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
      Contains documents pertaining to Blanche G. Moffitt, BJK's paternal grandmother.
    - Alysha Marie Moffitt, 1999-2012 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
      Contains documents pertaining to Alysha Marie Moffitt, BJK's niece and the daughter of BJK's brother Randy Moffitt.
    - BJK letters and postcards sent to parents Bill and Mildred Moffitt, 1952-2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
      Contains postcards and several letters sent by BJK to her parents, many describing international travel and tennis matches.
    - Moffitt family greeting cards and letters (1 of 4 folders), circa 1940s-2000s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
      Contains greeting cards and letters given and received by and amongst members of the Moffitt family, including BJK, father Bill Moffitt, mother Betty Moffitt, and brother Randy Moffitt.
    - Moffitt family greeting cards and letters (3 of 4 folders), circa 1940s-2000s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Moffitt family genealogy, 2011 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
      Contains correspondence and notes on Moffitt family history and genealogy compiled and sent to BJK by Donald Moffitt.
- Series II. Albums, 1940s-2010; 19.5 Linear feet in 7 record cartons and 7 flat boxes
  Series II contains all scrapbooks and photo albums in the collection. Album types include scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, albums containing a combination of clippings, ephemera, and photographs, and albums of solely photographs. The albums document the personal and professional life of BJK and family, including her childhood and early career, tennis career, the evolution of women's professional tennis, including the Virginia Slims Circuit, the TeamTennis league, and various events attended by BJK. Albums date from the 1940s to 2010.
  Related Materials
  Additional clippings are located in Subseries VII.A Clippings. Additional photographs are located in Series VIII Photographs.
  - BJK relatives, childhood, and career (4 folders), circa 1940s-1970s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5-8)
    Disassembled binder containing a wide variety of photographs of BJK relatives (mostly unidentified), BJK's childhood, and BJK's career.
  - Moffitt family (4 folders), circa 1950s-2000s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-12)
    Disassembled binder containing various photos of BJK, Randy Moffitt, and parents.
  - BJK tennis career (2 folders), 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13-14)
    Disassembled binder containing photographs of BJK playing tennis and newspaper clippings of BJK profiles and career news. Photographs include many early tennis career shots at Long Beach and a few match shots from Wimbledon. Articles cover 1960s Wimbledon matches.
  - BJK early Juniors career and Long Beach (2 folders), 1953-1959 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15-16)
    Disassembled binder containing photographs and newsclippings from BJK's youth tennis career and other junior players in Long Beach, California.
  - BJK Girl Scouts scrapbook, circa 1956 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4A)
    Wooden scrapbook created by BJK with Girl Scouts insignia on cover and containing tennis newspaper clippings and ephemera.
  - Clyde Walker and Long Beach recreation, 1959-1988 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    Disassembled binder containing newspaper clippings, photographs, and letters primarily documenting BJK's early tennis career, tennis coach Clyde Walker, and junior tennis players of the Long Beach, California area.
  - Clippings and photos album, circa 1959-2006 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4B)
    Contains letter from the Southern California Tennis Association regarding the 1960 Junior Wightman Cup, clippings over the course of BJK's career, comic strips, clippings on the death of BJK's father, and prints of digital Moffitt family photos.
  - Early tennis career clippings, 1956-1960 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4C)
    Album containing newspaper clippings and a few letters from BJK's early tennis career. Topics and competitions covered include tennis coach Clyde Walker, various Long Beach Juniors tournaments, Juniors Novice tournaments, and the U.S. Girl's Lawn Tennis Tournament.
  - Southern California Tennis Association Junior Wightman Cup Team, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 5)
    Album of newspaper clippings primarily covering the Wightman Cup team and BJK's early tennis career in Long Beach, California.
  - Wightman Cup Team, 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4D, Volume 1)
    Contains photographs, clippings, and letter from the United States Lawn Tennis Association office for matches from 1959-1961 and the 1961 Wightman Cup.
  - Wimbledon clippings, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 6, Volume 1)
    Album contains newspaper clippings primarily covering the Wimbledon tournament of 1962 with additional clippings covering BJK's career.
  - Wightman Cup, 1963 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4D, Volume 2)
    Contains newspaper clippings, photographs, letters from the Wightman Cup 1963 and additional matches of the year, newspaper clipping reporting on BJK and Larry King's engagement, and several polaroid shots of BJK and LK.
  - BJK career clippings (2 folders), 1963-1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18-19)
    Disassembled binder containing newspaper clippings covering BJK's tennis career. Topics include 1960s Federation Cup matches, 1960s Wightman Cup matches, and 1960s Wimbledon championships.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1965 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 1)
    Album containing newspaper clippings on BJK tennis career in 1965, many covering Wimbledon and the Wightman Cup.
  - BJK and Larry King wedding "candid previews", 1965 September (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - BJK and Larry King "Our Wedding", 1965 September 17 (Offsite-box 7, Box 7A)
  - Clippings and press scrapbook, 1965-1974 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 1)
    Album containing newspaper clippings covering BJK's tennis career, including various women's singles tournaments, the Fed Cup, and Wimbledon championships.
  - Clippings scrapbook, 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 2)
    Album containing newspaper clippings on BJK tennis career, including the U.S. Lawn Tennis Association rankings, and competition at the Davis Cup, Fed Cup, South African tennis championships, Wimbledon championships, and Wightman Cup.
  - Life Magazine album, 1967 (Offsite-box 6, Volume 2)
    Album presented to BJK from the editors and photographers of Life magazine containing photographs of BJK competing at the US Open Forest Hills 1971 and of BJK with Larry King and Randy Moffitt.